{"tossups": [{"question": "Monks in this country accidentally altered the dangerous confluence of three rivers when they built the Leshan Buddha. A tomb containing a mercury river and an army of (*) Terracotta soldiers honors this country's emperor Qin Shi Huangdi, who began building this nation's defense against the Huns. For ten points, name this nation, home to a Great Wall.", "answer": "People's Republic of China (accept Middle Kingdom; accept Zhongguo)", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "People's Republic of <b><u>China</u></b>", "acceptable": ["People's Republic of China"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept Middle Kingdom; accept Zhongguo"}, {"question": "In a novel by this author, Hank Morgan takes over Merlin's position through time travel. This author of A Connecticut Yankee in King Arthur's Court wrote a novel in which the deceitful Duke and Dauphin try to trick a boy who travels with Jim down the (*) Mississippi River. For ten points, name this American author of Huckleberry Finn and Tom Sawyer.", "answer": "Mark Twain (accept Samuel Langhorne Clemens)", "subcategory": "American Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "Mark <b><u>Twain</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Mark Twain"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept Samuel Langhorne Clemens"}, {"question": "This force is related to an accelerating observer by the Equivalence Principle of general relativity. Spacecraft can speed up by using this force as a \"slingshot.\" Galileo used two balls of different (*) masses to demonstrate that the pull of this force is constant, causing acceleration of 9.8 meters per second squared. For ten points, name this force that pulls objects toward large masses like the Earth.", "answer": "gravity (accept gravitational force)", "subcategory": "Physics", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>gravity</u></b>", "acceptable": ["gravity"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept gravitational force"}, {"question": "Martin Bormann was the private secretary of this political party's leader. Paramilitary wings of this party included the SS and SA, and this party's propaganda was organized by Joseph Goebbels. The Beer Hall Putsch in (*) Munich in 1923 tried to bring this party to power, and it ruled its country from 1933 to 1945. For ten points, name this socialist political party that ruled the Third Reich of Germany under Adolf Hitler.", "answer": "Nazi Party (accept National Socialist German Workers' Party or NS(DA)P; accept Nazi Germany; accept Adolf Hitler before \"this political party\" is read; do not accept \"Socialists\" alone; do not accept \"Fascists\")", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Nazi Party</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Nazi Party"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept National Socialist German Workers' Party or NS(DA"}, {"question": "In a work in this genre, produced by Sergei Diaghilev, Prince Ivan spares the life of the title Firebird. Another work in this genre traditionally includes thirty-two fouette \u0301s \ufffc \ufffc \ufffc \ufffc \ufffc performed by a woman who plays both Odile and (*) Odette, residents of the title Swan Lake. Jete \u0301s \ufffc \ufffc \ufffc and plie \u0301s are choreographed steps in, for ten points, what form of artistic dance?", "answer": "ballets", "subcategory": "Other Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>ballets</u></b>", "acceptable": ["ballets"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A group of texts found in these buildings at Saqqara describe a king hunting and eating the gods. Graduating sizes of mastabas were used by Imhotep to create Djoser's (*) \"stepped\" one of these buildings, and three of these structures belonging to Menkaure, Khafre, and Khufu were built near Giza. For ten points, name these enormous structures used to bury Egyptian Pharaohs.", "answer": "Egyptian pyramids", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Egyptian pyramids</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Egyptian pyramids"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Composition of these mathematical objects make the codomain of one of them the domain of the other. The vertical line test can easily determine whether a given graph describes one of these objects. In these relations, every input has exactly (*) one possible output. For ten points, name these mathematical objects, often written in \"f of x\" form, often taught in algebra as \"machines\" that turn a number into a new number.", "answer": "functions", "subcategory": "Math", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>functions</u></b>", "acceptable": ["functions"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A character in this novel is stretched to over ten feet tall after trying to appear on TV by using a shrink ray. Mike Teavee and Augustus Gloop accompany this novel's title character as he tours a food plant with his (*) Grandpa Joe, after he finds a golden ticket in a candy bar. For ten points, name this Roald Dahl novel in which the title boy inherits the legacy of Willy Wonka.", "answer": "Charlie and the Chocolate Factory (do not accept Willy Wonka and the Chocolate Factory)", "category": "Trash", "subcategory": "Trash", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Charlie and the Chocolate Factory</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Charlie and the Chocolate Factory"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "do not accept Willy Wonka and the Chocolate Factory"}, {"question": "On this date in 1929, several members of Bugs Moran's gang were killed, probably on the orders of Al Capone. This Christian feast day celebrates a saint who, according to legend, broke Roman law by performing (*) weddings for soldiers. A Prohibition-era gangster massacre took place on, for ten points, what holiday now often celebrated with flowers and written expressions of love?", "answer": "February 14 (accept St Valentine's Day or St Valentine's Day Massacre)", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>February 14</u></b>", "acceptable": ["February 14"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept St Valentine's Day or St Valentine's Day Massacre"}, {"question": "In one work, this man argues about holiness with Euthyphro but learns nothing to help him in his upcoming trial. Later, Crito tries to buy this man out of prison, but he refuses to escape his death penalty for (*) corrupting the youth of Athens. For ten points, name this ancient Greek philosopher who was executed via a cup of poison hemlock.", "answer": "Socrates", "subcategory": "Philosophy", "category": "Philosophy", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Socrates</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Socrates"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This element's four valence electrons allow it to form four bonds with other elements. This element's allotropes include diamond, graphite, and stable nanotubes, and an isotope of this element with an atomic mass of (*) 14 is used in archaeology for radiometric dating. For ten points, name this element, the focus of organic chemistry, with atomic number 6 and atomic symbol C.", "answer": "carbon (accept C before it is read)", "subcategory": "Chemistry", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>carbon</u></b>", "acceptable": ["carbon"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept C before it is read"}, {"question": "Characters with this profession include Ornstein, the captain of Gwyn's Four in Dark Souls. In Hearthstone, taunt minions can be killed by the battlecry of a \"Black\" one of these (*) warriors, who declares that \"none shall pass\" in reference to a skit from Monty Python and the Holy Grail. For ten points, name this class of warriors that, in video games, often fight dragons with swords.", "answer": "knights (accept Dragon Slayer before \"Hearthstone\" is read)", "category": "Trash", "subcategory": "Trash", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>knights</u></b>", "acceptable": ["knights"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept Dragon Slayer before \"Hearthstone\" is read"}, {"question": "This biblical figure was thrown in jail for refusing the romantic advances of Potiphar's wife. This man slipped a silver cup into a bag of grain after his brothers, including Gad and Judah, sold him into slavery. This brother of (*) Benjamin was Rachel's first child, making him the favorite son of Jacob. For ten points, name this biblical man who owned a beautiful coat.", "answer": "Joseph", "subcategory": "Religion", "category": "Religion", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Joseph</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Joseph"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This author of \"The Rhodora\" and the Harvard address \"The American Scholar\" wrote that \"a foolish consistency is the hobgoblin of little minds\" in one essay. This man rented his pond to Henry David Thoreau, a fellow (*) Transcendentalist. For ten points, name this American author of essays like \"The Over-Soul\" and \"Nature.\"", "answer": "Ralph Waldo Emerson", "subcategory": "American Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Ralph Waldo Emerson</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Ralph Waldo Emerson"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This project included man-made sections like the Gaillard Cut and Gatun Lake, and it was completed in 1914 due in large part to William Gorgas's efforts to control malaria and yellow fever outbreaks. This 48-mile-long structure included three (*) locks to help boats cross between the Atlantic and Pacific. For ten points, name this Central American engineering project.", "answer": "Panama Canal", "subcategory": "Geography", "category": "Geography", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Panama Canal</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Panama Canal"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "One of these events radiates from Eltanin and Rastaban. Another of these events appears to originate from the constellation Perseus, as seen from the ground, and occurs each year in August. The (*) Draconids and Perseids are examples of these events, which arise from Earth passing through the debris path of a comet. For ten points, name these brilliant celestial displays in which hundreds of \"shooting stars\" appear.", "answer": "meteor showers", "subcategory": "Other Science", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>meteor showers</u></b>", "acceptable": ["meteor showers"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "In a painting by this artist, five peasants gather around the title food under the light of a single lantern. The Potato Eaters is by this man, who created a still life with Sunflowers while living in Arles. This man painted the village of Saint-Re \u0301my \ufffc \ufffc \ufffc \ufffc \ufffc under a (*) swirling sky while institutionalized for cutting off his own ear. For ten points, name this Dutch painter of Starry Night.", "answer": "Vincent Willem van Gogh", "subcategory": "Visual Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Vincent Willem van Gogh</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Vincent Willem van Gogh"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "These organelles are plastids that replicate independently in the mesophyll of leaves. Within these double-membraned organelles, a fluid called stroma surrounds grana, stacks of thylakoids that carry out (*) light-dependent reactions. For ten points, name these cell organelles that contain chlorophyll, a green pigment that helps conduct photosynthesis.", "answer": "chloroplasts", "subcategory": "Biology", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>chloroplasts</u></b>", "acceptable": ["chloroplasts"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "In a short story written in this language, the book The Combed Thunderclap is kept in the infinite \"Library of Babel.\" A poet wrote in this language that \"tonight I can write the saddest lines\" as part of his (*) Twenty Love Poems and a Song of Despair. For ten points, what language was used by Jorge Luis Borges and Pablo Neruda, writers from Argentina and Chile?", "answer": "Spanish (accept Espan \u0303ol)", "subcategory": "World Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Spanish</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Spanish"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept Espan \u0303ol"}, {"question": "A wagon train retreating from this battle was caught at Monterey Pass, but George Meade couldn't catch up to it. During this battle, Lewis Amistead advanced to the \"High Water Mark of the Confederacy,\" although (*) Pickett's Charge failed to turn the tide of this July 1863 battle. For ten points, name this battle of the Civil War, whose site was made a cemetery after Abraham Lincoln gave a namesake \"Address\" there.", "answer": "Battle of Gettysburg (accept Gettysburg Address)", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Battle of Gettysburg</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Battle of Gettysburg"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept Gettysburg Address"}], "bonuses": []}